Well, at long last we have arrived at
the very last video of the entire
stinking APUSH curriculum. But go ahead
and stuff those emotions down deep for
now cuz we have one last bit of work to
do and that's to consider some of the
various challenges America has faced in
the 21st century. And I'll give you a
proper goodbye at the end of the video.
But for now, if you're ready to get them
brain cows milked one last time, let's
get to it. All right, so it was arguably
one event that shaped US policy in the
21st century more than any other and
that was the terrorist attacks of
September 11th, 2001. Now, you need to
understand that as the United States
emerged into the 21st century, the Cold
War was over, but radical Islamic
movements in the Middle East would take
center stage as the most challenging set
of developments to address. So,
hopefully you'll recall that the United
States had been deeply involved in the
Middle East for decades prior to this.
From the overthrow of the Iranian regime
in 1953 to supporting Israel in their
wars against Muslim states to the
Persian Gulf War, Americans just
couldn't seem to quit the Middle East.
And that involvement, not surprisingly,
had embittered many factions in the
Middle East who desperately wanted the
US out of the region and to stop messing
with their crap. And as it happened, one
of those embittered factions was a
militant pan-Islamic organization called
al-Qaeda led by a guy named Osama bin
Laden. Now, bin Laden had started by
aiding the anti-Soviet forces during the
Soviet-Afghan War and then intensified
his calls for retaliation against
America after the Gulf War and the
continuing presence of US troops in
Saudi Arabia. And more to the point
here, bin Laden was the mastermind
behind the September 11th attacks in
2001. So, on that morning, al-Qaeda
terrorists crashed two commercial
jetliners into the towers of the World
Trade Center in New York City and then
another into the Pentagon. And they had
also hijacked a fourth plane, but its
passengers fought back against the
hijackers, they crashed the plane into
the Pennsylvania wilderness. Anyway,
only a couple hours later, both World
Trade Towers collapsed killing nearly
3,000 Americans and it replaced Japan's
attack on Pearl Harbor as the deadliest
foreign attack ever committed on
American soil. Now, President George W.
Bush had entered office only a few
months before this attack and while his
campaign promises focused mainly on
domestic reforms, this attack
significantly shifted his focus to
foreign policy. And now let's consider
the effects of this attack and I'm going
to give you two. First of all, shortly
after this September 11th attack, Bush
vowed to retaliate in what he called a
war on terror. And to be clear, this was
not a war against a specific country
like the Vietnam War or the War of 1812
or whatever. It was a war against any
country that harbored or encouraged
terrorist activity. Now, the immediate
focus of the conflict was to capture and
kill Osama bin Laden who had fled into
Afghanistan where the Taliban government
had offered him protection. And long
story short, by 2002, American forces
had defeated the Taliban government, but
were unable to capture bin Laden who was
able to escape into Pakistan. And as a
result, the fighting continued and the
war in Afghanistan ultimately lasted 20
years, just outranking Vietnam as
America's longest international
conflict. And then the second effect of
the 9/11 attacks was another war in
Iraq. So, 2 years after starting the war
in Afghanistan, Bush declared that the
war on terror required expansion and he
set his sights on Iraq. Now, recall from
a previous video that George H.W. Bush,
George W. Bush's father, had prosecuted
a war in Iraq almost 20 years earlier
after Saddam Hussein had invaded Kuwait
in order to gain control over its oil.
However, Hussein was allowed to remain
in power after the conflict ended and as
a result, he ruled over his people as an
oppressive and brutal dictator. And
while Bush and his officials pointed out
that such authoritarian tactics hindered
the spread of democracy in the region,
their true motivation was to secure
access to Middle Eastern oil. And side
note, that's essentially the main reason
the US is going to go to war in this
period to protect its interest in
oil-rich countries. Like, it's not the
only reason, but it's certainly a big
one. However, Bush actually had no
compelling justification for starting
another war with Iraq. Like, yeah,
Saddam Hussein was a bad guy and all,
but it wasn't like he was posing any
real kind of threat to the United
States. But Bush was just itching to
start this war and that's when he
developed the Bush Doctrine. It said
that the United States should strike
preemptively if it was determined that
another country threatened American
safety. Now, in case it's not clear,
that was a massive departure from the
international laws of war which said
that a country could only rightfully
attack another if the other posed an
imminent threat of attack. Like, under
the old rules, if a guy was running at
you with a baseball bat, then you would
be entirely justified to give him a
proper smackdown because the threat was
very real. The Bush Doctrine, on the
other hand, asserted the right of the
United States to attack another country
if the US thought that that country
might be a threat in the future. And
that would be more like going to a
baseball game and deciding that you're
going to launch a ballistic missile at
the guy stepping up to the plate
because, you know, it's possible that he
could run after you and attack you with
that bat that he's holding. And so, Bush
declared without a single scrap of
evidence that Saddam Hussein was
developing weapons of mass destruction
and therefore met the requirement for
the Bush Doctrine smackdown. However,
American allies in the United Nations,
wanting to prevent this conflict,
demanded that Hussein allow UN
inspectors to search Iraq for these
WMDs. And to everyone's shock, Hussein
agreed. And then to no one's shock, the
inspectors found no evidence of WMDs.
But that didn't matter much to Bush
because he had already been gearing up
for war. And so, in 2003, American
troops invaded Iraq and in only a few
weeks had toppled Hussein's government,
although Hussein himself escaped into
hiding until he was captured later that
year. However, while the military
operation was quick and decisive, there
seemed to be no plan for how to
stabilize the country after its
government was dismantled. And as a
result, various Iraqi factions began
fighting each other for power and
fighting the Americans whom they viewed
as intruders. result was another long
and costly conflict that increased
rather than decreased instability in the
Middle East, all in service of
protecting American oil interests. All
right, so that's what was going on in
foreign policy land. But now let's
consider the developments that occurred
on the home front as a result of the
9/11 attacks. So, those terrorist
attacks had taken everyone by surprise,
not least the very intelligence agencies
that ought to have connected the dots
and seen it coming. Therefore, the Bush
administration moved quickly to heighten
security on the home front in order to
find any other terrorists that might be
still among the population. And to that
end, Bush initiated two big changes.
First was the passage of the USA Patriot
Act in 2001. So, among other things,
this law gave the federal government
almost unlimited powers to surveil the
American public's phones and emails and
other personal records in order to
uncover terrorist plots. Now, to be
clear, the law only allowed the
government to collect metadata, which is
to say every piece of information about
a communication except for the content
of the communication itself. And at
first, many Americans registered very
little complaint about their government
legally spying on them. And that was
largely because in the weeks and months
after the 9/11 attack, public sentiment
was united behind the idea of finding
the terrorists and making sure that
another 9/11 never happened again. And
then second, in the wake of the attacks,
Congress created a new executive cabinet
agency, the Department of Homeland
Security, whose mission was to develop a
national strategy and policy for
preventing future terrorist attacks. And
it was the largest reorganization of the
federal government in US history since
this new department was now the home of
dozens of other smaller agencies.
However, over time, the measures taken
by the Bush administration to carry out
the war on terror sparked some
significant debate. For example, some
Americans began raising the alarm at the
extent of the government's surveillance
of its own citizens under the Patriot
Act. And when the extent of this data
collection was leaked by NSA contractor
Edward Snowden, it sparked a heated
debate about whether this kind of
surveillance was a violation of
Americans' Fourth Amendment right to
privacy. And then the second example of
the debates would be the various human
rights violations that the
administration justified under the war
on terror. You see, while carrying out
the war on terror, the Bush
administration made a habit of capturing
suspected terrorists and shipping them
to an American-owned prison in
Guantanamo Bay, Cuba. And because this
prison was not located on US soil, the
Bush administration bypassed any notion
of recognizing their right to the due
process of law and legal counsel.
Furthermore, the Bush administration
took advantage of the murky geopolitical
status of this prison in order to
justify their policy of torturing
inmates in order to gain information on
other suspected terrorists. And once
news broke about the inhumane conditions
of the prison, some Americans and
several multinational organizations put
pressure on Bush to shut it down.
However, this prison is still
operational today and it has proved very
difficult for successive presidents to
close it even if they oppose its
continued operation. Okay, and finally,
let's talk about a significant
environmental challenge the US has faced
in the 20th century and that would be
climate change. fact that protecting oil
interests had led to several wars was
reason enough for a debate about the
concerning relationship America had to
foreign oil. However, at the start of
the 21st century, another related reason
presented itself, namely global warming.
So, by the year 2000, the fact that the
planet was warming had made itself clear
and scientists largely concluded that
this phenomenon was being caused by the
burning of fossil fuels like oil. And
trying to figure out exactly how to
respond to that crisis has become one of
the most debated issues of the modern
age. So, the international community has
recognized this problem and has come
together to attempt to reduce their
greenhouse gas emissions. first major
effort on that count was the Kyoto
Protocol signed in 1997 in which 37
industrialized nations agreed to limit
their carbon emissions. And then the
second major effort was the Paris
Agreement in 2015, which was looser in
its requirements, but included many more
countries who committed to lowering
their carbon emissions. However, the
United States has gone in and out of
this agreement depending on the ideology
of the current president. And that's
kind of a big deal since the US is
responsible for emitting between 20 to
30% of the total carbon contributing to
climate change. And that's largely
because the US is home to a handful of
powerful oil companies who successfully
lobby the federal government to keep
their products unregulated. Also, the
cause of global warming itself has been
the target of bitter ideological debate.
For example, some groups of conservative
Americans deny that climate change is a
cause for concern because the science is
wrong. You see, they claim that the
increasing temperature is caused by a
natural cycle of the Earth that has come
and gone many times and therefore any
legislative attempts to regulate
emissions is tantamount to a rejection
of free market economics and a return to
New Deal liberalism. And that is a
debate that, again, continues to this
present day. However, here's why I tell
you that even with all of these
challenges, the United States has
continued to be the world's leading
superpower in the 21st century and we'll
just have to see where that goes. And
that, my dear pupil, is the end of the
curriculum. So, let me just say that I
counted an absolute privilege that you
have allowed me a place in your life and
your education. And I want you to know
two things before we end. First, I am
cheering you on as you go to sit for
that national exam. And then second, no
matter what happens, I am proud of you.
You have worked so hard and you deserve
to know that there's at least one bald,
bearded, gap-toothed man here in Atlanta
that thinks you are pretty great. So,
good luck. I'll catch on the flip flop.
Imler out.